[Music]
Yeah.
Say it again. Good evening. Uh, welcome
to the August 25th Finance Committee
meeting. I am your host again, whether
you like it or not.
We're going to roll right into new
resolutions, starting with temporary
resolution 7325.
coming through water water pollution
control. Mr. Wing.
>> Yes. Thank you, Mr. Chairman. Uh I'd
like to invite Denise Cruz up or whoever
will be answering questions about this.
And uh while she's on her way up, uh the
background on this is council in 2022
previously authorized the not to exceed
amount for the North Water Treatment
Plan plant project uh not to exceed $90
million. and we are edging closer and
closer to that number and it looks like
we will exceed that slightly due to uh
some upcoming change orders. I'd like to
have Denise describe some of those
change orders, please.
>> Thank you. So, as we go through the
project, um and uh Councilman Wing was
correct. Uh Stephen, originally I asked
for $90 million on the project. Um the
original contract was 95381.
We had $5 million budgeted for
contingency. So, at that point, we're
over the 9 million. Anyways, um we do
have some bigger uh changes coming up as
we move into plant startup in two weeks.
Um the two big ones are um grading and
seating and landscaping on the site. Um
we deferred that uh mainly to see what
the site was going to look like and um
how much money we had to spend on this.
Uh so that's going to come in
um under 500,000 but there's a lot of
areas to be planted. Uh we did not go
overboard on the landscaping.
Um, the other one is paving. And again,
that was an item that we didn't know
what what everything was going to turn
out to be. We knew uh the new plant
obviously, but we're um doing some uh
paving in the old plant and in the
driveway leading up to the swimming pool
due to construction traffic. So again,
um I think that was about $300,000.
Um, so the the change order we're
working on right now is sitting
someplace around
um 600,000
and that will push us up to about 8 n
89500,000
someplace in that area. Um, and then
that's obviously not the final change
order because we've still got another
month to to find out what's not going to
work. Um, so regardless, we're going to
be over 90,000. Stevens asked for
another million for 91. This is all just
a paperwork uh for the C for the city
auditor. It's not any new money.
All right, questions.
>> Actually, I do. Um, so I've been on the
water committee for four terms and um I
don't remember I mean spending I mean
it's just constant constant constant you
know and and Arcadus has been with since
94.
>> Mhm.
>> Okay. So, have they ever come here and
done a presentation or anything? Because
I don't know that I've ever seen them
the whole time. I I I mean, you know,
they're the consultants and I mean, we
just keep spending and spending on this.
This is just over the top. And I know
you can say, "Oh, it's a big water
plant." But you also told us last Monday
during water meeting there might be
another big cost again on something. I'm
really lerary with all this stuff. I
would like to have Arcadus come and you
know do a presentation of what all
they've done
since you guys are all I just you're
very confused. I would like to also have
and you always talk about your punch
list.
>> I would like to have and be sent to
council the amount it was supposed to
cost for this plant. I would like to
have the current debt
and um if any payout already that that
you've paid. I would like to have all of
council to get the dollar amount on
this.
>> Okay.
>> I think we all I think and and this is
taxpayer dollars. Um I just think that
um and then doing the
>> just just let me ask because I provided
this to Bob Wolfinger in the spring. He
did not share that with you.
>> Did anybody get anything?
>> That would be no. But once but but once
again
>> it's my understanding I've not seen
anything but that some of that was
incomplete
>> and he had asked for clarifications
>> so I don't know if that was
>> he didn't ask me for clarification but I
just to to try and figure out what you
want and I may give you a call Becky.
>> No don't give me a call. Send me an
email.
>> No no no to see exactly what you want.
>> Oh I have it right here. I I think all I
I think the main thing that she's asking
for so we originally
approved the construction contract at 85
million and some change and then you
always have your
>> contingency dollars. So right
>> whatever you've spent or however so
really five million and some change is
your contingency dollars. So that's
that's what I believe Miss Tiner is
asking to see is where are all those
contingency where those contingency
dollars being spent or have been spent
on any of your change orders basically.
>> Okay.
>> Right. Does that make sense? Well, that
and and you know, Stephen had come a
couple meetings ago and there was money
asked for because some things weren't
done or there was something, you know,
um you know, every single dime needs to
be accounted for here because after what
you uh informed us last Monday, there's
going to be possibly a even bigger cost
than this plant and I'm really concerned
about that.
>> No, no, there's it's not a bigger cost.
We're we're looking at at the next phase
of the western transmission line which
is about 15 million
>> but I don't remember that being said
before.
>> Okay. So specifically for the plant you
want to see
>> because we need to keep track of the
dollar amount here.
>> So the contingency dollars what you
spend it on,
>> right? Okay.
>> Does that make sense?
>> I I have a spreadsheet. Um but Stephen
won't be back until the 5th. So it may
be Any
other
>> after he gets back?
>> Uh, we approved $2.5 million of an
increase in Arcadus' fee a while back.
Is that part of this 5 million that
we've you utilized at this point?
>> No.
>> So, that's over and above the
contingency.
>> Yes.
>> Interesting.
>> Tom, do you have a question?
>> Well, I he asked most of it. Uh I wasn't
here when the
you know we made the decisions were made
on the plant and the legislation was
passed. So just to make sure I
understand. So originally the budget was
$85 million with is it a $5 million or a
$10 million contingency because I heard
a couple things here.
>> So we put in our loan we put $5 million
for contingencies.
>> Okay. Um and so the contract was 85
million 381
is is what Stephen asked for the
authorization to enter into the contract
with Kakosi.
So um
that was contract Stephen asked for $90
million to allow us to enter into
contract up to $90 million. So even if
you take the contingency, the 5 million
on top of Kakosin's contract, it was
always going to be over 90 million.
We just
tried to work in round numbers and hope
for the best. So if you take Kakosin's
$95 million $381,000
contract and add 5 million to that,
you're going to be over 90 million.
>> Okay.
And and we can't sign anything over 90
million without your authorization.
>> Okay. And that doesn't include the 2 and
a.5 million that we approved for the
engineering.
>> That does not include the engineering
contract.
>> So
I I have to ask what what other kind of
things are floating around out there
that are large. Like when I say large, I
mean anything over
$100,000.
Other than the Darren, can you think of
anything other than landscaping and
>> paving? I I can't. It doesn't come to
mind. I'll have to look and see what's
on the change sheet.
>> Okay.
>> We have it.
>> You have it. Okay.
>> Mr. Chairman, if I could.
>> Yep.
>> So, I think certainly everything in this
plant is itemized. All the expenses are
documented. Um, not only do we document
them locally, but OWDA
also receives uh reports what monthly?
>> Pretty monthly.
>> Monthly and uh obviously the plant is
inspected and at some point it'll be
turned over us for operation which we
expect to be October 1st. But along the
way, along this uh travel to build this
essentially $95 million water plant,
we've experienced uh shipping delays
internationally,
uh COVID,
uh tariffs,
uh if anyone sitting in council, and I
was one of them, people voted uh in
favor of this plant being built, we knew
that at some point there would be
additional cost.
And so we initially estimated that at 90
$90 million. It's going to exceed that,
not significantly, but it's going to
exceed that. But there's been a lot of
things thrown at the city of Lancaster
in in this u effort to build this plant
that were not foreseen by anyone at any
level of government operations because
worldwide we've experienced things that
just haven't happened before. The
tariffs are new and I can tell you just
on a a water plant purchase order that
came across in February, we had a cost
of the item being at $2,500 and when it
was repriced uh a couple of months
later, it was $4,000. That was
attributed to tariff cost.
So I assume the water plant is not
immune from that and that that it's seen
impact from tariff and and cost on
shipping and and delays in shipping and
not saying that justifies all the
additional expense but it certainly
explains some of the additional expense.
So I take take that into consideration.
>> Chairman Skunover, may I? Mhm.
>> I I appreciate the fact that that
tariffs exist and that we have had
increases due to the pandemic, all of
those things. My concern and I believe
some of the council members concerns lie
in the fact we don't have a good picture
of what you owe, meaning the department,
what it owes in relation to debt service
and how it's proposing to pay for it. So
in addition to a review of the
contingencies,
we would like a big picture of exactly
what is owed on what and the payment
schedules associated with that and how
we propose to pay it all back.
>> Okay. Like I said, I provided that to to
Councilman Wolfinger in the spring.
>> He's not here.
>> So it it's not unavailable. It's just
Steven's on vacation.
>> But I also think it needs updated
because we have had additional expenses
and you're asking us to authorize
additional expenses. So I think we need
to we need to update that.
>> That's bad.
>> I'm I'm sitting here as a member of the
committee and I'm we've discussed all of
these things.
The questions that you're asking, I feel
that they've addressed them more than
adequately at the committee meetings.
And I don't understand why one of our
members is asking these questions. And I
I feel like another thing that's
happening and and if you come to the
committee meeting, you hear these things
and maybe it's our fault for not
reporting this, but I I know I've heard
this on the council floor before that we
rushed we were rushed to get into this.
And I I feel like we made some mistakes
very early that cost a lot of money.
And
so you're at $90 million. Do you quit?
Are we quitting?
Do we not finish? Is anyone suggesting
that? I'm I'm sure they're not. But I'm
I'm saying is what I'm saying is
part of what's happened happened because
someone was in a hurry. Haste makes
waste. I don't know. I I grew up hearing
that and we did. And now we're paying
for it.
>> That's it.
>> All right. Real real quick because we're
already like down the rabbit hole. Becky
asked his questions on the floor so
everybody can hear them because the
meetings aren't the committee meetings.
Not too many people come. Right. The
same time you just had your water
meeting, your committee meeting. Are the
minutes out for that yet?
>> Uh Mondays will be this week. the rest
of them are but last week
>> some of us haven't that haven't been to
that meeting haven't seen those minutes.
So that's the other reason that during
council last meeting we started the kind
of round the table hey what's going on
in your committee. So I think
although some of those are valid we also
have we've asked for Denise to send some
documents which we should have before
the next meeting.
Right.
>> I will try. Like I said, Stephen's on
vacation.
>> It It's available. You guys can make it
happen. I'm I'm confident you can make
it happen. This is three readings so we
can have more of this discussion next
time
once we all see the meeting minutes. We
all see all of that. So, I don't mean to
be cutting everybody off to move on to
the next piece, but clearly
there's some contention here and we can
That's why we do three readings, right?
So, we got a little time. Denise can get
the stuff. We can look at it. We have
another round of questions next time and
I have zero problem bringing it up in
finance next time if we need to or we
can wait until the regular meeting. Is
everyone good with that?
>> Okay.
>> All right. you're staying up here for
the next this is like your meeting. You
might as well just stay up there. So,
temporary resolution 7425
again through water water pollution
control. Uh yes, this piece authorizes
um the mayor to submit the loan
application for the uh Frederick Street
sewer separation project that we've
talked about previously. And uh that's
up for construction next year if I
recall correctly. Is that correct,
Denise?
>> Correct. This this authorizes the mayor
to submit a loan application to Ohio EPA
for the water pollution control loan
fund. Frederick Street is um project is
to install a storm sewer from Mount
Pleasant to Feder's Ron. It's a project
that was identified in the long-term
control plan. Um so we we are mandated
by Ohio EPA to do this project. Um,
Stephen is choosing to fund part of it
through a loan. That was um, one of the
things he looked at when he did his rate
study, balancing debt versus cash. Um,
so this has been on the table for loan.
Um, and the loan application is due in
November.
It's about a $3 million project.
>> Okay. Any questions on this one?
Seeing none, we'll move on to temporary
resolution 7525.
That's coming through finance. That
would be myself uh with a second of Miss
Bitler. And I'm going to defer this one
to the auditor, please.
>> Thank you. Um, yes. This one is we just
received the uh second half special
assessment from the Fairfield County
Auditor's office and the crack crystal
ball guess that I did this time last
year for what's going to be collected
for the downtown uh special improvement
district and the special assessments.
Um, I was short by $8,31211
in my guess. Um, and we did receive the
settlement uh just the end of last week
or well at last week and um I need to
get payment made to the uh SID um so
they can have th that those monies that
were collected. So um this is just um
I'm going ahead and cutting the check
throwing the account into the red so
they can have their money. So it'll be
coming uh this week for them. But I just
needed to get those monies budgeted that
we received that I didn't anticipate
last year.
>> Any questions?
>> It's three readings. Okay,
>> it's council's pleasure. I'm fine with
that.
>> Anybody?
Okay, we'll stick with three unless
something changes. Okay.
>> All right. Temporary resolution 7625
through water water pollution control.
Mr. Wayne.
>> Yes. I'll invite Denise back up. Oh,
there you are. Um,
we've gone out to bid. Uh, we authorized
going out to bid on the Lawrence Street
Pump Station Replacement Project. And
um, this authorizes the engineering
contract.
>> Correct. Lauren Street Pump Station sits
across from the sanitation maintenance
building. In fact, it was built to serve
the sanitation maintenance building. Uh
it also serves South Ewing Street and um
the rest of sanitation kind of down to
Sugar Grove Road.
uh it's at the end of its useful life
and we also have had several inquiries
about extending the service area for
that pump station to serve the um JKB
industrial site um instead of them
having to go up to the railroad tracks
and back around. Um so we did a request
for qualifications for the project. We
had three engineering firms submit.
Uh after the committee reviewed it, we
selected Arcadus and they have um
submitted a proposal um for design,
construction administration and
construction inspection services of
$400,000.
>> Questions?
What's the uh projected cost for the
facility itself? construction cost.
>> Um we're looking we're thinking at this
point because it hasn't been designed um
that it's going to be roughly four to $5
million.
Any other questions?
I just have one quick one. when you
reference in the legislation the
committee that picked Arcadus,
>> can you I I'm sure I've heard this
before, but who's the committee that
selects out of your qualified?
>> So, when we do a request for
qualifications, we we have a group
review it, it was uh Stephen and myself
and Curtis.
>> Okay.
>> With them.
All right. Any other questions? So that
is three readings with Mr. Hail. Um,
sorry.
>> I'm assuming we're taking out bonds for
for this.
>> At this point, we anticipate paying cash
for this one.
>> Pay cash. Okay.
>> All right. So, I have three readings
with Mr. Als is your second.
Michael.
>> Yes, that's correct. Okay.
>> All right. Uh temporary resolution 77.
>> Yes. Um this authorizes the mayor to
enter um or to submit a state capital uh
grant application for the replacement of
the Tiki water line of the water line on
Tiki Lane.
>> This is an annual piece. Um every year
the city can um submit up to two
applications to the Ohio Public Works
Commission. Um and Kurt and utilities
alternate on who gets the number one. Um
because we did not submit a number two
last year. Kurt submitted for Arbor
Valley Drive. So it's our turn this
year. Uh we're submitting the Tiki Lane
water line replacement. This is from
Sheridan to Monmouth. It's to replace
the line that has suffered several
leaks. Um several big leaks. Um we
anticip this is currently out out for
design. Uh the application is due the
1st of October.
Um and this is just a requirement of the
application.
>> Okay. Any questions?
Seeing none. I have
Miss Tener as your second.
>> That's correct.
>> Three. Do three readings. Okay.
>> All right. Any other resolutions we need
to discuss?
No. Uh temp uh new ordinances starting
with temporary ordinance 4025.
It's coming through code enforcement and
zoning. Mr. Sully.
>> Thank you, Mr. Chairman. Uh this
ordinance is to accept the final plat
for the Taylor commercial subdivision.
And I'm going to invite uh our city
planner, Chzine, to come up and
talk about this.
Good evening everyone. Uh this is the
final plat for the Taylor subdivision.
Just a kind of a brief um overview. This
if you're not familiar, the property is
at west of Edy Road between Memorial
Drive and Columbus Street. The plat that
you should have with your packet um
outlies easements. It outlies um
infrastructure. You will notice that
um across lot two and three there is an
access easement for ingress and egress
of the for the general public. Um this
easement is considered a private
easement and it's to be maintained open
and in good repair by the owners of lots
two and three. Um this easement is not a
public road maintained by the city.
Becker Way is the public road. It is
built between lots two and three. Um and
it'll be extending from Memorial Drive
to North Columbus Street.
It's just kind of a brief um layout of
what is shown on the plat. And then
um we do have the Caso team and Mr.
Taylor here if they would like if you
would like to hear um from them.
>> Joe.
>> Uh thank you, Mr. Chair. I just have one
question for you, Chasine. um those
easements that you described in Becker,
those are meant to accommodate the
traffic that you could potentially see,
right? I've had some constituents reach
out to me on that. I just want to
confirm that detail with you.
>> Yes, there was a traffic impact study
and the engineering team looked at that
um and this was what they have um
came up with to kind of ease that
impact.
>> All right. Thank you so much.
>> A quick question. I think we're all
aware of what's happened down around the
mall with that private drive, right?
What do we have in place to protect the
city that'll make sure that these are
maintained in good working order since
they're going to be privately
maintained?
>> So, it is um this is laid out on the
plat that Stephanie, I don't know if you
want to pitch in, but it is laid out on
the plat who would be maintaining these
um private areas.
>> Yeah, she's correct. We've fixed
language in our plats to make sure that
the city is no longer responsible for
private easements. Becker Way will
actually be dedicated though as a public
road eventually between lots one and
two. Um so it will be built to city
standards initially and the city
engineer and LDOT are responsible for
making sure that happens. Um but once
it's dedicated to us then at that point
it's ours. The private easement though
will be the responsibility of the
property owner and they could make an
arrangement with the the person who
leases the property. Um but regardless
it will not be the city of Lancaster
maintaining that that easement
>> and we have no authority over making
sure they do maintain it. Right. Um,
we have some authority. Uh, essentially,
yes, we could file a civil suit if
necessary, but it shouldn't come to that
because it's in the plat.
>> Thank you.
>> Any other questions?
No, I have one and I'm I even have
contacts in and I'm So that easement
you're speaking of that goes through two
and three, does it pop out for access on
Edy and on Columbus?
>> So
is that what
>> it Yeah. So from I believe um it goes
from Edy across
>> um but it would go to Becker like from
Edy to Becker.
>> So anyone can turn into lot three from
Edy Road.
>> Correct.
>> So I know there was discussion a while
ago about So if you're coming onto Edy
from Memorial
turning left onto that access. Is that
what we're looking at? They're going to
be able to turn left
>> from Memorial or
>> No, they're turning on to Edy from
Memorial
>> and then being able to turn left on
Becker as opposed to going up to the
light at Columbus.
>> Oh, wait.
>> I think I'm confused about what you're
asking. So, they're turning
>> No. So, there's an access road that
comes out on Edy.
>> There is an access road.
>> It's an access.
>> Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes, it's an access
easement for public use. So,
>> so they'll be able to turn left
>> from Ed Road on.
>> Yes. It's my understanding that the
traffic impact study looked at that and
whatever they decided in terms of them
and the engineer how it operate. Yeah.
>> All right.
>> Does that make sense what I said to the
rest of you?
>> Yeah.
>> Now, it does.
>> It was just like I I feel like two years
ago when when we first talked about it,
that was something we were having a
conversation about. So,
>> so you're concerned with traffic backing
up from there onto 33?
>> Yeah,
>> I got you. Cuz that road we just widened
it and fixed the backing up onto Edy all
the way to Columbus,
>> right?
>> And now someone wants to turn left in
there. But I get I guess you see that
you're talking about the traffic state.
Most people that are coming on to Ed
from Memorial end up getting in the
right lane and turning right onto
Columbus. So, I get it. Okay,
>> couple questions. Uh, so just to
clarify, which lot is a Chick-fil-A
going to be in because that's that
really
>> really I mean when we're talking about
cars turning and things
>> just follow the traffic line is what you
would just be
>> the reason I ask is where how is this
going to pile up? I mean I don't know if
you've driven by a busy Chick-fil-A and
watched their drive-thru. I mean it's an
incredible process how they do it. I
mean, it's amazing, but
>> I don't want to see that spilling out on
the 33. That would be
>> So, they will be intended for lot three.
>> Okay.
>> Everybody will be so excited just like
White Castle when White Castle opened.
Do you remember that traffic nightmare
for like six months?
>> Oh, yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> So, but I am concerned though that
>> what you're talking about there is
access too from 33 I see here.
>> Yeah.
>> Um
Is uh Becker Way only going to be
accessible from northbound traffic or
can incoming traffic into town turn left
across 33 and on to Becker?
>> So there will be a
So you can turn left, but you won't be
able to come out Becker and turn left to
get onto Memorial. Yeah,
>> but you can turn left coming towards
town on Becker or on 33 onto Becker.
>> Yes.
>> Okay.
So, left in, right out. Okay. All right.
Everybody get it?
>> Cool.
>> I have another question.
>> Yes.
>> What is the urgency for suspension?
>> Um, there has been some delays in
getting this project started. Um,
and Chick-fil-A has
they kind of do a fall schedule. I don't
know if someone can explain this a
little better than I, but they have a
fall schedule, a spring schedule that
they plan all of um their openings on.
Yes.
>> So, they're kind since the delays and
working out the infrastructure and
everything that's happening for the
development um they're kind of getting
behind on that schedule. They still want
to be able to get some paving done, get
some work done this season.
You didn't see their construction of
stores in the news today like
>> it's coming.
>> Any other questions?
>> And then they can't um move on that
until the final plat has been approved.
>> Would you like to hear from
>> Eric from Casto?
>> Yep.
>> Good evening. Thank you, Chasm. Good
evening. My name is Eric Leewoods with
Casto here on behalf of the Casto team
and Taylor. Uh thank you again for the
opportunity to be here. I'll be I'll be
brief. Uh just to touch on the traffic
question. Uh as Chasel and Stephanie
alluded to that was all vetted and
approved as part of the traffic study,
the idea with the construction of Becker
Way and the private access drive was to
make sure that the flow of traffic was
safe, efficient, and taking into account
who the tenant was. So the site plan,
all of that has been very carefully
vetted and planned. Uh the traffic study
has been looked at a number of times and
that has been approved by the city
engineers office. Um the in terms of the
urgency and then need for suspension as
Chasyn has uh referred to there's a
number of delays. This project um in
terms of getting it going is a developer
funded public road and is in being
completed in complement to the safety
project which obviously opened a few
years ago. Um and so the idea is to try
and get the public road Becker Way
finished in time for uh the Chick-fil-A
opening. And so the timing with paving
and getting that done before plants
close and everything else in advance of
the planned opening. So there's some
construction timing that fits into that.
So there's uh uh making sure that we
meet the city specs in terms of delivery
and and the city staff has been
fantastic in getting to that process. It
has been a long time coming. So happy to
answer any other questions, but we're
very appreciative of the time tonight.
Um
thank you very much. Any other
questions?
Seeing none. All right. Thank you very
much.
>> Okay. Thank you.
>> Moving on. Temporary ordinance 4125
coming through water water pollution.
Mr. Wing.
>> Yeah. So, this is an update to the uh
city's wastewater rates and it is the
subject of a presentation during the
regular meeting and um if you're all
right with that, Mr. Chairman, we can
have discussion and questions during the
presentation.
>> Everybody okay with that? Denise, you're
okay with that?
>> Yeah.
>> We don't have to kill it twice.
>> Okay. All right. Uh, I have three
readings. Mr. Als is your second.
>> Yes, that's correct. Okay.
>> Thank you.
>> Thank you, Denise.
And now it turns into the law committee
show temporary ordinance 4225
coming through law committee. Miss
Crates.
>> Yes. Thank you. Um 4225 and 4325 are
related. 4225 is to repeal part of the
zoning code and 4325 is to amend part of
the parking code. Both are related to
the commercial vehicle parking. And
after the update to the zoning code in
2023, there resulted a conflict with
that parking code that wasn't realized
until some recent parking issues over in
the Parkland Drive area. Um because of
some safety concerns with school buses,
pickup, drop off, things like that, we
want the administration would like to
repeal the zoning code, keep the parking
code with some updates. Um and then also
we need suspension because right now
they cannot enforce either code because
of the conflict. So we need to clean it
up and then that way they can enforce
the code as well. Law director Hall or
service safety director Woody or mayor,
would you like to add anything to that?
I don't. That was perfect. Thank you.
>> Very well said.
>> Agreed.
>> So, it will be a suspension and I have
Ms. Mrs. Bitler and Mr. Bischack
>> respectively.
>> All right. Any questions on those?
>> I have one question. So, just to be
clear, the zoning code that we're
repealing,
>> that will be addressed later.
>> That was part of So, that is the
conflict piece to the parking.
>> Yeah. So that's being eliminated,
>> just that part.
>> Correct. And then I I spoke with
Councilman Sullie earlier. I I explained
to him that he's the chair of the code
enforcement and zoning committee, and I
didn't want to step on his toes and just
make something up. Um so we're sending
it back to his committee, and he's more
than happy to to work with the members
of his committee and determine what
you'd like to see uh moving forward with
regard to the zoning code aspect of it.
>> Okay. Thanks, Stephanie.
>> Yep. And I apologize, I didn't catch if
you were speaking to 43 at the same
time. I do want to make everybody aware
that um the mayor indicated some of you
took issue with the 14,000 pound weight.
Um first of all, I will say that I have
no idea what a vehicle weighs, period. I
don't know the difference between GVWR
and payload. I have no clue what any of
these mean. The goal was to fit any
residential or any um any personal
vehicle essentially into a residential
neighborhood. So some folks drive F350s.
Um, Michael Wings got some kind of
monster he likes to park on the street.
You know, these big things. We just
wanted to make sure that if it was a a
resident who lives on that street that
they would have the ability to park
their personal vehicle um on the street
where they live, right? Um but the mayor
indicated some people thought 14,000,
which was the initial that's in your
packet, was too high. So, we moved that
back to 10,000 GVWR.
That means anything to you? It
>> does. um that that's what it is now. Um
the goal was to I think have smaller
vehicles um rather than something that
could fit into the 14,000 range. So
I'll let him address if he wants to
>> 10,000 is a equivalent to a one ton
non-commercial vehicle. Um 14,000 is a
box truck
which we currently do not allow on city
streets. So, we would be allowing a much
larger vehicle that would possibly
obscure traffic control devices and
certainly take up more space.
The idea of moving this from uh what was
a a 3/4tonon pickup to a one- ton was
because one ton has become a pretty
standard non-commercial pickup truck and
we we didn't want to make a person
person's personal vehicle um illegal to
be parked in the in the residential
area, but we also don't want box trucks
parked on every block in the city
either. So that's why
>> Cory
>> the recommendation Larry
>> I provided pictures to
>> he did provide pictures
>> trucks that would qualify under and and
there were box trucks and stick trucks
and a tow truck and many vehicles that I
know we we did not intend to allow park
on the street. So
>> Right.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. Any other questions?
>> Kathy,
>> I just have one um clarification um
please. So, under uh 4325
in 35116,
um the packet I have tonight says uh
nothing over 14,01.
Is that should that be 10,000 is what
you're saying?
>> Yes, ma'am. I I walked in a piece with
just that change like I described. Yeah,
I gave it to the clerk. I apologize. Um
the preamble didn't change at all, so we
don't have to, you know, do any more
readings or change anything else. Just
the number. Yes, ma'am.
[Music]
Any other questions? Becky,
>> I just have a question. Unless I'm
totally miss I've read through this and
I can't remember, but can they park like
in the box truck or the bigger truck in
in like their driveway
off the street?
>> Yes.
>> Okay. Currently, yes.
>> Currently, yes.
>> Okay. Yes. But
>> be a zoning issue.
>> Exactly. Yep. Just take it out.
Any
other questions on those?
>> So, we'll have a star version. Is that
it?
>> No.
>> Okay. We don't
>> Well, we didn't read it.
>> Okay, good.
>> I just thought we should clarify in case
anybody was thinking about this that if
somebody's actually making a delivery or
they're temporary out there, you know,
you get like a landscape crew or
somebody
>> is there, you know, obviously to cut the
lawn.
>> There's in the ordinance. They're not
going to get ticketed correct while
they're working. And you know, we're
going to use common sense here.
>> Loading, unloading, and actually working
from the vehicle is excluded.
>> I just wanted to point that out.
>> All right. Thank you. Uh 4425
again coming through committee, Miss
Crates.
>> Yes. Uh we had legislation passed in
2024 regarding a moratorum that was
placed on adult use cannabis
dispensaries within the city and we were
required to revisit that before January
1st, 2026. uh the law committee did
revisit that which included a
presentation from a dispensary company
and after discussion because the state
legislation remains pending and without
that legislation is unclear whether the
city's primary benefit of having a
dispensary which is additional tax
revenue would even come to fruition.
Therefore, the law committee is
recommending that we extend the
moratorum for at least two years and
revisit that honor before January 1st,
2028 with the next council and law
committee. Hopefully, the legislation at
the state level has, you know, finalized
by then.
>> Questions, comments, concerns?
Seeing none, moving on to 4525 also
through the law committee. Miss Crates.
>> Yes.
Um, this one is because the city's
improvements inspections are handled by
multiple inspectors in different areas
and departments. The current process
includes delays uh between interdep
department communications and handoffs.
The city wants to allocate all of these
fees into a single fund and use those
fees for a single inspector who will
cover all inspections. The city has a
qualified FTE and if it did not, this
structure could allow for them to use a
single contractor. Service safety
director. Mayor, would you like to add
to that? Again, I think you summed it up
very nicely. I think that mayor and I
have been working on trying to improve
efficiencies within the city and improve
our customer service and this is just
one of those measures that we think will
help both reach both of those goals.
>> Thank you. Uh Mr. Bisjek will be my
second and it's three readings.
>> Okay, any questions?
Okay, that is it for ordinances. I am
open for department updates if we have
any.
Nobody. I'm okay with that.
Mr. President, council meeting prep.
>> Thank you, Chairman Skoonover. As you
alluded to, we do have a presentation
tonight uh from uh our environmental
engineer uh regarding wastewater rates.
And we also have a presentation from
Lancaster City Parks, Superintendent
Steve Gayfield.
>> Great. Thank you very much.
Any other items for finance?
Seeing none, I ask I'll ask for a motion
to adjourn.
>> So move,
>> Mr. Sully. We are adjourned at 6:42.
The regular session of Lancaster City
Council will begin promptly at 6:50.
The Frankie Smith Funeral Home and
Crematory in Lancaster and the Johnson
Smith Funeral Home in Baltimore have a
long and wonderful history of serving
our community. Feel free to give us a
call at 740-653652.
Stop in and see us at either of our two
locations, 405 North Columbus Street in
Lancaster and 207 South Main Street in
Baltimore. Respect for tradition, regard
for change.
>> Hi, this is Jill Henwood with the
Victoria Players Children's Theater in
Baltimore. We are currently in our
eighth season thanks to local support.
This month, we are really excited to be
chosen as a recipient of the Buckeye
Cares program. That means Buckeye will
make a generous donation to help our
efforts with every vehicle they sell
this month. From all of us at Victoria
Players Children's Theater, we say thank
you, Buckeye.
[Music]
Heat. Heat.
Please rise if you're able and join in a
moment of prayer. Seriously, if you can
think of anything, give a shout. God
grant us the serenity to accept the
things that we cannot change, the
courage to change the things we can, and
finally the wisdom to know the
difference. Please join me in the pledge
of allegiance.
>> I pledge algiance to the flag of the
United States of America and to the
republic for which it stands, one nation
under God, indivisible, with liberty and
justice for all.
Now call the August 25th, 2025 Lancaster
City Council meeting to order. I'd also
remind all council members at this time,
please turn on your mics for purposes of
the meeting. Um, please call the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> here.
>> Mrs. Bitler
>> Mr. Bisjack
>> here.
>> Mrs. Kes
>> Mrs. Hoop
>> here.
>> Mr. Lockenberg
>> Mr. Skoonerberg
>> here.
>> Mr. Mr. Sully
>> here,
>> Miss Tiner here, and Mr. Wayne
>> here.
>> Let the record reflect all 10 members of
Lancaster City Council are present.
>> Reading and disposing of the journal.
>> I have regular meeting minutes dated
July 14th, 2025.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to receive and file the journal.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion, a second to receive
and file the journal. All those in
favor, please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> I. All those opposed, same sign. Reports
of city officials. I have nine of them.
Um, email dated August 13, 2025
regarding July 2025. Re revenue report
submitted by tax commissioner Amy
Hamilton. Email dated August 18th, 2025
regarding cyber security training
submitted by council member Kite. Email
dated August 18th, 2025 regarding Taylor
final plat submitted by city planner
Chelyn Carter. Series of emails dated
August 18th through the 24th, 2025
regarding wastewater rate study
submitted by law director Stephanie Hall
and environmental engineer Denise Cruz.
Email dated August 21st, 2025 regarding
September um public works meeting uh
submitted by council member Becky Tiner.
Email dated August 24, 2025 regarding
explanations on temporary resolutions
73-25
and 74-25 submitted by environmental
engineer Denise Cruz. Email dated August
24th, 2025 regarding explanations on
temporary resolutions 76-25 and 77-25
submitted by environmental engineer
Denise Cruz. Email dated August 24th,
2025 regarding explanations on temporary
ordinance 41-25 submitted by
environmental engineer Denise Cruz. And
finally, email dated August 25th, 2025
for zoning changes short for short-term
rentals submitted by council member
Elena Hope.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to receive and file the reports of city
officials.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion, a second to receive
and file the reports of city officials.
All those in favor, please signify by
saying I.
>> I.
>> All those opposed, same sign. We now
move on to communications.
>> I have mail received August 13, 2025
regarding multifamily homes submitted by
Sycamore Ridge Lancaster um and
affordable housing development. Email
dated August 14, 2025 regarding purchase
order data. Um public records request
submitted by Hammedi Kama with the data
branch research team. Email dated August
15, 2025 regarding purchase order data.
Public records requests submitted by Woo
Park with the data branch research team.
Series of emails dated August 15 through
the 25th of 2025 regarding FOIA requests
for Hunter Hill, 587 Elizabeth Drive,
Lancaster. Uh submitted by Brie Pollen
with AEI Consultants. Email received
August 18, 2025. Um the September guest
speakers submitted by Tracy Thompson,
president of Lancaster Fairfield County
Landlord Association.
Mail dated August 19th, 2025 regarding
multifamily funding programs submitted
by Vira Fairfield and Marian Development
Group.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to receive and file the communications.
>> Second. We have a motion, a second to
receive and file the communications. All
those in favor, please signify by saying
I.
>> I. All those opposed, same sign.
>> We now move on to the portion of our
meeting for special presentations,
beginning with our first special
presentation this evening from the
Lancaster City Parks Superintendent
Steve Gayfield.
>> Good evening, Mr. President, members of
council. Thank you for the opportunity
to come speak to you tonight and give
you an update on what the parks have
been working on. Um, I'd like to focus
on three areas. Our personnel, our
programs, and our projects. Projects are
probably the ones that you'll have the
most questions about, but I wanted to
give you information on the rest of
that. Also, um, over the last year, we
had a wave of retirements, some
expected, some not expected. So, we have
been understaffed until just recently.
Um, we, if you weren't aware of it,
Jennifer Shamblin, who's been
functioning as the recreation supervisor
of the department, um, was recently
promoted to be the assistant
superintendent. She's still going to
operate recreation, but she's providing
assistance with to to me some with some
administrative task and she's also
taking over some projects. Um, one of
them is going to be Elwood Park, which
I'll talk about here shortly. We also
are in a process of finishing the hiring
of a new parks facility supervisor. I
expect him to start sometime in the
middle of September and with that we'll
be back to full staff so we can
hopefully start catching up on some of
the things we've not addressed as well
as we normally do. Um programs, while
it's been a wet year, we did
successfully operate and navigate
through our spring and summertime
program schedule. Some of the
highlights, I won't cover all of it
because you all have a big agenda, I
see. Um, first spring soccer had 646
Lancaster residents in that youth soccer
program, 120 teams total because we play
with some other teams throughout the
county also and other communities.
Spring flag football had 108 Lancaster
residents in it and 23 teams total again
playing with teams from communities
within the county. Adult kickball which
I believe the city staff had a team and
I believe maybe the service safety
director and did the auditor play also?
Oh yes, Nitra played. Um we had seven
teams in that. We continue to see that
grow. The pools this year, while it
wasn't a great year for the pools,
especially early in the season because
it was so cool and rainy, um we did have
at Tiki over daily visits, we had 14,225
people over two and a half months. At
Miller, we had 7,78
for a total of over 21,000 daily visits.
um in two pools over two and a half
months. That's a large number for a
community of this size. So, the pools
are being very well used. And now we're
continuing with our fall programs.
Soccer's taken off. Flag football is
taking off again. We had a cornhole
tournament this last weekend downtown.
So, you'll continue to see those and the
special events that are coming up. So,
that kind of covers programs. For
projects, I wanted to talk about some of
the larger projects. We had several
small projects, but the ones we've
completed as far as larger projects was
tiki pool. The slide needed to be reel
coated. You have to do that
periodically. The slide is nearing end
of life. Um but by regel coating it, we
can continue to use it um for some we'll
keep we'll keep maintaining it as long
as we can. Let's put that way. That was
a 21,000 or $22,000 project. Oliveale uh
roof. Last year, the Oliveale seniors
actually paid for half of the roof to be
installed. Um the agreement was we would
pay for the other half. So this year we
did phase two, the roof was installed.
Um we estimated the work at around
60,000. The total was 56,927
and some change. And the good news was
with the olive seniors went out and
found a grant and they actually paid
30,000 of that. So, we saved a
considerable amount of money by
utilizing our partnership with the
Aladdale seniors. They really stepped up
and helped us out this year. So, I
wanted to say thank you to them. Um,
finally, if you didn't know, we did do
some storm water improvements at um
Rising Park. Um, that was completed here
recently.
If you remember, if you've ever been in
Rising Park, after heavy rains, the
basin down by the pond, the large pond
would normally flood and hold water. Um,
the good news is is the storm water
improvements were done before the
flooding that affected so many people so
badly in the in the community. Um, and
the very next day there was some water
there, but it was not ponded like I I
didn't I expected the whole area to be
full of water and there was a little bit
around one of the trees. So, um, thanks
to the engineering department,
specifically Jeff Beck for helping out
with that because it is going to allow
us to move forward with paving the rest
of the park. It didn't make sense to
pave the road when the drainage wasn't
fixed first because then you have to dig
up the road to fix the drainage. So, we
took care of that and now we'll move
forward with more paving and rising.
Finally, projects that large projects
that are in process. I mentioned Elmwood
Park improvements. That's a $225,000
project. That was a grant received from
the state. Um, it is a playground
replacement and Jen Shamblin is going to
take that on and that's become her
project. I started it. it's going to be
her opportunity to become a project
manager. Um, we started this spring by
removing the old tennis courts which
were not repairable and were in terrible
shape. So, we removed them. We seated
it. We uh probably needed to do a bit
more grading to make it level because
the idea is to turn that into green
space so that the youth sports teams
have another place to practice because
they're always looking for a place. So,
that part of it is done. Currently, we
have a playground that's going to go in
over there. That's the rest of the
project. Um, we actually had some we had
kids vote on several designs. Um, they
chose one. Actually, this Wednesday at
6:00, Jen is going to be over at Elmwood
Park. Um, we contacted the neighbors to
let them come look at the design so they
can see what we're going to put in and
if they have any questions or anything,
they can ask us at that point. So, so
that is moving forward. We expect to
order the playground and have it
installed this fall. um the future
Bowers Park um which I have and asked
several questions about. Um the fall
work started a few weeks ago. I believe
you all heard that um from the Ohio
operating engineers. They have completed
the final grade and return top soil to
one field. So that field is ready for us
to actually grass seed um put ball field
infield dirt on and potentially put in
back stops this fall. they have started
on doing the same thing on a second
field. So, and that's what we that's
what they told us they would complete
this year was two fields. So, the two
back fields are finishing the top soil
and grading there. And then when that's
done again, we expect to be able to put
grass seed um infield dirt and hopefully
back stops up on that. Obviously, those
fields have to grow in. There is no
water in that park, so we can't water
the grass seed. So, we have to get the
outfields established by letting god
rain on it to be honest. Um, so we'll
we'll get them as playable as quickly as
we can. The good news is is they
actually have already started on the
subgrade and the layout of a third
field. So, three of the four fields are
going in right now. They may, depending
on weather, be able to complete that
third field this fall. Also, if it rains
a lot, they won't be able to do it. You
can't move top soil when it's soaking
wet. Um that was one of the holdups this
spring when they didn't come out and
work. So um with that that means the
park staff is working on seating the
outfields. We're getting all the
information together. We're going to do
it this fall. Um we're working on the
infields. We are going to put some
drainage in the infields. The plans that
were developed for the park did not
include drainage on the infields. Um we
feel that is a mistake. So we're going
to put it in ourselves. Um because while
the while those fields should drain well
the way they're graded um we would
prefer to be better be safe than sorry
so they're playable more often. Um, and
then finally, just to if we need to
speed the process up, I'm meeting with
two LMN, which was the design architect
for the park. Tomorrow, we're going to
do a walk through to see where the
progress is, and they are preparing a
proposal if we decide to move forward
with hiring a contractor to speed the to
speed the project up. So, that's where
Bowers Park stands uh as of tomorrow
when I meet with the with the
architects.
And then finally, just to give you a
heads up on um what I call the
re-imagined Miller Park. Obviously, we
have to wait for the water plant to be
completed before we can get too far into
it, but we did put out an RFQ, a request
for qualifications for architects to
take our concept design that's been out
for a couple months now, and move that
into um full full construction
documents, biddable documents, all of
that information that closed Friday. We
did receive um did receive one and we're
in the process of putting together a a
committee kind of like Denise did with
her RFQ of city staff to review that and
make a recommendation. So that is in
place and then also with Miller and Tiki
both um we did decide to go ahead and do
a pool assessment because one of the big
questions that come is coming out of
Miller Park is what's going to happen to
the pool? Well, we did hire a firm um to
come in and we're going to they're
actually this this Thursday we're having
a meeting with them where they're going
to present um their assessments of the
current status of the pool, give us some
ideas of both Tiki and Miller, give us
some ideas of what we could and could
not do with them, and then actually move
forward from there into doing public
input on what people would like to see
and uh what, you know, doing some of
that more uh public outreach work to see
what people are looking for especially
residents in town. So with that, those
are kind of my updates. I don't want to
take up too much of your time. I'd
entertain any questions you might have.
>> Thank you, Superintendent. Questions
from council. Council member Bisjack.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. Uh just on the
subject of Bowers Park, what is your at
this point with everything going on and
I appreciate the update very much
because I've had a few constituents
reach out to me about the ballparks as
well, but what is your estimated total
timeline to complete you know, till
completion for the park. I know I know
you provided for the first three, but
I'm just curious what's estimate and I'm
emphasizing the estimate part. So,
>> um if if we stick to the course that was
started many well, five, six years ago
at this point with Ohio operating
engineers, um they will get those fields
in this year, two fields. Um we should
be able to get at least the the grass
seed and the infield dirt on it. with a
ball field infield dirt. The longer, to
be honest, the longer it sits, the
better it is, but obviously you can't do
that. People need their fields. Um, if
the grass seed comes in, we could
potentially have two fields depending on
if we get road and drainage finished.
Um, we would have two fields sometime
next year.
the what they had told us when we talked
to them last year and we planned this
was they could do two fields this year,
complete the last two next year and then
we would do the same thing that we're
doing this fall. We go in, seed them,
put the infield dirt on, put the back
stops up. I would expect fields at that
point to be playable um 2027.
That's if we continue on the route we're
going. Um, using Ohio operating
engineers saved us approximately if you
the engineers estimate from two years
ago was just around $600,000 for all the
grading and the road work and that
they're doing. Um, so if we move forward
with a contractor and we bid it and go
that it'll obviously go faster and I
can't give you a timeline for that.
>> Thank you.
>> You're welcome.
>> Any other questions from council
members?
Council member Tener um Elwood Park. I
really appreciate you guys doing
something over there because it's needed
to I used to play tennis over there
years ago, but um uh everybody's okay
with that. The neighbors, everybody's
okay with what you're doing over there.
Yeah, we have not had any any negative
feedback on
>> because that would be a really nice park
that I mean it's really needed and and I
really appreciate with the Olive Dale
thing that they're pitching in and
helping out and doing things because
they they really do need to do that. And
um anything about skate park is that
going to be in the plans of this thing
that you're talking about over by
Miller?
>> Sure. The first or the RFQ that went out
was for phase one, which is basically
what we have funding for. skate park is
going to be part of the future phases.
It's not part of the the design right
now.
>> Where will that do they think it might
be?
>> Um I'm we're thinking that it's probably
going to move over to the other side of
the of the river over by the old what we
call the community building, the old
Sherman school,
>> by the football field there. the whole
the whole concept plan includes
additional parking, um a pedestrian
bridge so you can cross the river, um
all of that. That's all part of the the
plans for that.
>> Thank you.
>> You're welcome.
>> Thank you, Council Member Als.
>> Uh yes. Um the letter that we received
for that from Judy Edwards, one of her
concerns was the appearance of there are
piles of gravel and all kinds of things
at Bowers Park. Mhm. It
>> is any of that going to be taken care of
this fall or
>> Well, the the actual the big pile of
dirt that I' I've asked about quite a
bit. That's actually the top soil. They
removed the top soil to do the grading
and that's the top soil they're putting
back on. So, some of that will be gone.
It already is if you go out there and
look.
>> I'm talking about the other pile.
>> The other pile, the grindings,
>> the taller pile.
>> Yeah, that's the grindings. That is
intended for the roadway going in. Um,
so that probably won't be gone this
fall. I mean, I would expect them to not
want to put that down until they get the
construction equipment and get the
fields actually put in place and then
put that in to make the roadway to go
in.
>> What time are you meeting tomorrow?
>> Um, 10:30, I believe.
>> Okay. Thank you.
>> And I will I'll send you a email and
verify that.
>> Thank you.
>> Any other questions from council
members?
Seeing none, thank you for your
presentation tonight, superintendent,
>> and thank you for the opportunity. Have
a great night.
>> Our second presentation is a rate study
presentation provided by our
environmental engineer, uh, Denise Cruz.
Um, do we need lights off for this dog
for the back?
>> We will see.
>> We will.
Yeah, I think she's got it on now.
>> I always do this. I'm sorry.
>> You're good.
So, first of all, I got voted to do the
presentation because I talk faster and
can condense it down, but uh Darren Drum
and Curtis Wam are here and they're
going to come up to help answer
questions uh when I'm through all of
this.
Um so, this tonight is the 2025 rate
study update.
Uh we did a rate study in 2022 and
normally we do rate studies for five
years. Um and we based that rate study
on what we projected as industrial
flows. What we what we had been led to
believe. Um in that study we adjusted
rates among the various classes. We
adjusted the capacity fees and we
recommended rate increases for 23, 24,
25, 26 and 27. Um, and those were
adopted. Wastewater rates were adopted
by council. Water rates were adopted by
the service safety director.
In the meantime, uh, industrial flows
did not increase as much as predicted.
Um so we got a little nervous.
Um project cost increased due to all
those things the mayor talked about
inflation, labor costs, supply chain
time delays. Um we also had additional
EPA regulations
including lead copper asset management
risk assessment and increased sampling
requirements.
Um and this is kind of never ending. We
were in a call this morning with Ohio
EPA and they want to reopen the
long-term control plan and look at what
the next phase on that might be.
Um, so looking at all of those things,
as I said, we got nervous in water and
water pollution, decided that maybe we
needed to go in and take a look at this
midterm so we didn't get a surprise at
the very end and we could make gradual
rate adjustments.
Um, I did send you the redacted rate
study. It was redacted in accordance
with the Ohio Revised Code. Um, if
you've got questions on something that
was redacted, uh, let us know and, uh,
we can talk you through that.
Um, so what the 2025 rate study found on
the wastewater side, which is what's
before you tonight at council, um, was
a, um, we were in good shape. what we
predicted would work a 3% 3%
um
for 26 and 27 we extended it two more
years because we're two more years into
a five-year rate study. So that
projected out um
so that that that worked out fine. on
the water side. Um what we found was
um even with the recommended rate
adjustments,
um we were going to be short and a lot
of that was due to the fact that um the
division of water was requesting $2
million for asset management
preventative maintenance projects. We
are just so behind on things. Uh we went
for years without rate increases. We
went for years saying if we can just get
the south water plant paid off, we can
put money into the system. And when we
paid off the south water plant, we
started on the north water plant. So,
division water has a huge backlog. They
requested $2 million a year.
Um, so th this would be what it would
look like.
Then we talked about the philosophy of
water charges and there's basically
three philosophies. They're all valid
depending on what you want to do. The
first philosophy is what we currently
have which is a declining rate. Under
declining rate system, a larger portion
of the cost is pushed down on the lower
water users and we the larger water
users get a break on uh each um 100
uh cubic feet of water that they use. Um
uh in a declining water rate, you it's
done to encourage big water users to
locate. Well, guess what? We got our big
water user.
Flat rate communities
um are communities that basically their
philosophy is a gallon of water is a
gallon of water and it doesn't matter if
it's going to your house or if it's
going to the hospital or if it's going
to an industrial user. A gallon of water
costs what a gallon of water costs.
Uh then there are a few communities that
have increasing rates. Uh these
communities um tend to want to conserve
their water capacity.
So they tend to want to have smaller
users or encourage water um
conservation.
So we looked at us being a declining
rate community and said,"Well, what if
what if we go to a flat rate?" And we've
been a declining rate community for
about 10 years.
So if we would go to and phase out our
declining rates,
this is what the rating rates would look
like.
Um, and as you can see in 26 we're
starting to bump up those higher water
users.
Um, and then in 27 everyone will be
paying the same. So we did a phase into
this.
So on the water side this is what it
would look for a residential user. Um,
the rates actually come down. In 26,
we're proposing a residential user will
not see a rate increase.
Um, in 2027, they'll see a 3.8% rate
increase. And in 2829, instead of an 8%,
they'll see a 7.4% rate increase. This
will all generate the same amount of
money that we needed um and identified
in the rate study.
On the wastewater side,
there is a small increase in 26 66 cents
a month. Uh that has to do with the base
rate, not the um per gallon usage.
Um and that goes 1.8 and 27 and 2.9 and
28 and 29. So again, under the the 3%
that um we initially predicted
just as a comparison
uh because somebody asked me, these are
some surrounding communities.
Um I included Delo and Delaware County
because they serve the developed area
around Delaware. The city of devel city
of Delaware does not serve all that
development up there. It's the county in
Delo.
Um, so you can see yes, our rates are
higher, not as high as Anesville, but
higher. Newark is currently undergoing a
rate study because they desperately need
improvements in their plants. So, we
expect Newarks will come up closer to
what we're seeing once they get the rate
study done.
Um, so the next steps, sewer rates are
set by city council. you have the
legislature before you. Um the current
rates already include a 3% for 26 and
27. We're proposing take those back and
put the new rates in
um
and add 2829 which is not currently in
the legislation in the ordinance.
Water rates, I want to make clear, are
set by the service safety director, not
by city council. So, we're providing you
this information tonight, just so you
know what's going on and you can see the
big picture.
Uh, we made this presentation to our
committee in May. We've submitted it
tonight u for three readings. So, we um
if you pass it, it will become effective
September 22nd and the new rates will go
into effect January 1st.
And that's what I have. If anybody has
some questions, I'm going to let the
guys come up.
questions from council members for
improvements.
>> While you all think, I thought I'd take
the opportunity to introduce myself. I'm
Curtis with them. I haven't been here
too long. I've been up here once, but
I'm the superintendent of water pushing
control and uh happy to answer any
questions you have.
>> Thank you, Council Member Bitler.
>> Uh thank you, Mr. President. I just have
um a couple of questions basically that
are related to non-metered accounts.
>> Yes.
>> Um so, um how many non-metered
residential accounts do we have?
>> Um
only a handful. And I'm going to say
less than a hundred. They're mainly the
county um subdivisions around the city
that we serve. Um
and I can't even tell you what they are
right now. Um
>> that's okay. I don't
>> but because we don't provide water,
they're charged to non-meter and and we
assume you uh five I think five units
>> per per home. Okay.
Um and then the other question is um
there's discussion and I I don't think
this is new um
water used um and not measured by a
water meter and this I believe is for uh
the industrials
um they can meter it themselves correct
and but how are we how are we getting
readings from those that are
self-metering
>> that are self-metering so if they have a
sewer meter those are read by So, we are
reading their meters. Thank you very
much.
>> Um, and I should say that we still have
the summer average meter,
>> right,
>> reading. Um, so for people that that use
water to to water their lawns and and
things like that. On the wastewater
side, they do an average. So, summer
usage is is kind of evened out based on
their winter usage. And you can find
information on that on the web page if
you've got questions.
>> Thank you, Denise. Thank you, Mr.
President.
>> Thank you, council member. Any other
questions?
>> I guess we come back to earlier this
evening when we were having the
presentation about the the water plant,
the north water plant. it. I think it's
imperative that council and also um the
community knows, you know, what our plan
is, what what what is our debt service,
what are our rates, what's our income,
and how are we paying for it, and making
sure that we're doing everything that we
need to do to address our future needs
and the needs that we're doing now. So,
if we could get that information, we'd
be very appreciative. I'll be glad to
provide a summary, but that was all
spelled out in the rate study. We
projected those capital plans and our
debt service.
>> I appreciate that. I appreciate that
it's in the rate study that what you're
doing. The debt's not. So, I think what
we need to see is it all in one place
all all in a very easy to understand
format for folks here.
>> Yep.
>> That service is included in rate study.
>> Okay. Thank you.
>> Yeah, I'll be glad to provide it.
>> Thank you.
Any other questions?
>> Thank you for your presentation.
>> Thank you.
>> Petitions and memorials,
>> there are none this evening.
>> Thank you. We've now reached the time
for permission of voters and taxpayers
to address council. Uh the process is a
threeminut u opportunity to address
council. You must approach the podium,
sign your name, address, and uh um on
the um provided clipboard. Um is there
anybody here this evening who would like
to take this opportunity to address
Lancaster City Council?
>> Seeing none, we thank you for your
attendance this evening.
Reports of standing committees.
>> I have two water pollution committee
agenda dated August 16th, 2025.
Submitted by Mr. Wing. Finance Committee
Agenda dated August 25th, 2025 by
submitted by Mr. Skunover.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to receive and file the reports of
standing committees.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion and second to receive
and file the reports of standing
committees. All those in favor, please
signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> All those opposed, same sign. Reports of
special committees.
>> I have none.
>> We have no reports from special
committees. Uh we don't have a public
hearing. We're going to move on to the
reading of resolutions beginning with
the third reading of temporary
resolution 6525.
>> A resolution to appropriate from the
unencumber balance and amend the
certificate of appropriations with the
county auditor in the city income tax
fund 2016
to accommodate increased refunds in 2025
and to pay to replace the backup sewer s
server. My mind's on water for the
income tax department for the
cloud-based system. This is through
finance committee. Mr. Skunover, Mr.
Sully.
>> Council member Skunover.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
that council pass and grow and enter
upon the written record temporary
resolution 6525.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion and a second to pass
and gross and enter upon the written
record temporary resolution 6525.
Any discussion? Council member Skinner.
>> I have none. Thank you. Hearing no
further discussion, please call the
role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Bitler,
>> Mr. Bischeck,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Kates,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Lockenberg,
>> Mr. Scooter,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Sully,
>> Miss Teener, yes.
>> And Mr. Wing,
>> yes.
>> Temporary resolution 6525. Passes 10 to
zero. We'll now move on to second
reading, beginning with temporary
resolution 6725.
a resolution authorizing the city
administration to act on behalf of the
of the city of Lancaster to enter into
any and all agreements or settlements
necessary to participate in the new
national opioid settlements with the
Alvogen Inc. Amneal Pharmaceuticals Inc.
Appex Inc. Hikamite Pharmaceuticals USA
Inc. And Divior Inc. Myand
Pharmaceuticals Inc. Sun Pharmaceuticals
Industries, Inc. and Zitis
Pharmaceuticals USA, Inc. and to declare
an emergency.
>> Yay.
>> I practiced that one.
>> You need to do it again though.
>> Yeah, one more time.
Still second reading.
>> I was proud of myself.
>> From from the law committee.
>> Oh, I'm sorry. This is the law
committee. Mrs. Crates and Mr. Bishack.
>> Council member Kates.
>> Yes. Thank you. Uh second of three
readings. Second of three readings on
temporary resolution 6725.
Temporary resolution 7025.
>> A resolution authorizing the service
safety director to enter into an
engineering agreement for updating the
division of water asset management plan
as required by the Ohio Environmental
Protection Agency and Ohio Water
Development Authority through water
water pollution control committee. Mr.
Wing and Miss Tiner.
>> Council member Wing. Yes. This is the
second of three readings.
>> Second of three readings on temporary
resolution 70-25.
Temporary resolution 7125.
>> A resolution to authorize the service
safety director to advertise for a
request for qualifications and issue a
request for proposals for a design
professional
for design and construction
administration of the Ed Road fire
station project and to declare an
emergency. This is through safety
committee. Mr. Bisjack and Mr. Sully.
>> Council member Bisjack.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. This will be
the second of three readings.
>> Second of three readings on temporary
resolution 7125.
Temporary resolution. We're moving to
first reading now. Temporary resolution
7325.
>> A resolution to amend permanent
resolution 95-22
authorizing the service safety director
to enter into a contract for the
construction of the northwater treatment
plant replacement project. Water water
pollution control committee, Mr. Wing
and Mr. AS.
>> Council member Wing.
>> Yes. This will be the first of three
readings.
>> First of three readings on temporary
resolution 7325. Temporary resolution
7425. A resolution to authorize the
mayor to prepare and submit an
application to participate in the Ohio
Environmental Protection Agency water
pollution control loan fund program for
the planning, design, andor construction
of the Frederick Street sewer separation
project to execute contracts and
agreements as required and to designate
a dedicated repayment source for the
loan. This is through water water
pollution control committee, Mr. Wing
and Miss Tiner.
>> Council member Wing.
>> Yeah. This is the first of three
readings.
>> First of three readings on temporary
resolution 7425.
Temporary resolution 7525.
>> A resolution to increase receipts,
appropriate from the unencumber balance,
and amend the certificate of other
sources and appropriations with the
county auditor in the special
improvement district fund 2020.
This is through finance committee. Mr.
Skunover, Miss Mrs. Bitler.
>> Council member Skunover.
as the first of three.
>> First of three readings on temporary
resolution 7525. Temporary resolution
7625.
>> A resolution to authorize the service
safety director to enter into an
agreement for the engineering services
for the Lawrence Street pump station
replacement project. This is through
water water pollution control committee.
Mr. Wing and Mr. Ales.
>> Council member Wing.
>> This is the first of three readings.
First of three readings on temporary
resolution 7625.
Temporary resolution 7725.
>> A resolution to authorize the mayor to
prepare and submit an application to
participate in the Ohio Public Works
Commission State Capital Improvement
Program and to execute execute contracts
as required. This is through water water
pollution control committee. Um Mr. Wing
and Miss Tina.
>> Council member Wing. Uh first of three
readings.
>> First of three readings on temporary
resolution 7725.
We'll now move on to the reading of
ordinances. Beginning with the third
reading of temporary ordinance 3125,
>> an ordinance to amend the Lancaster
codified ordinances, part 11, planning
and zoning title 3, zoning and property
restrictions, and to adopt chapter 1131,
short-term rentals. This is through code
enforcement and zoning committee, Mr.
Sully and Miss Soup.
>> Council member Sley. Thank you, Council
President. Um, before we uh proceed on
this, I would like to open up for uh
discussion with council. We've had a
couple things come up here this week and
before a uh put this forward, I just
going to invite any member of council to
>> okay for discussion.
>> Should we have should we have the um
>> I'd like to make a motion to table.
>> So, we have a motion to table. Do we
have a second? We have a second. We have
a motion and a second to table. Um, this
is a non-debatable motion. Please call
the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Bitler,
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Kit,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Lockenberg,
>> Mr. Skoonberg,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Sully,
>> Miss Tiner,
>> yes.
>> And Mr. Wing,
>> Motion to table passes 10 to zero. Uh
temporary ordinance 31 25 is tabled.
We'll move to the second reading of
ordinances beginning with temporary
ordinance 3625.
>> An ordinance to amend permanent
ordinance 54-24, the non-union pay
ordinance and to declare an emergency.
This is through code enforcement and
zoning committee. Mr. Sully and Mr.
Lockenberg.
>> Council member Sie.
>> Hi. Uh thank you, Mr. President. Um, I
would like uh to let our city u safety
director just kind of uh cover this
again exactly what we're doing with this
legislation.
>> Yes. Thank you, Councilman Sie. Um, as
you recall at our last uh council
meeting, I indicated that we have a
current position in the city in our
utility departments that somewhat
underutilized.
and the individual in that position used
to work for the building department had
started getting trained on zoning and
zoning inspections prior to going to the
utility department. Um, since our zoning
individual retired earlier this year, we
are wanting to move that individual from
utilities into the zoning. However, to
do that, we needed to add a additional
zoning inspector in our city ordinance,
allowing us to move and pay that person
under the zoning
under the zoning budget.
and I'm happy to answer any additional
questions that you have.
>> Thank you, M. Mr. President. I would uh
like to make a motion that council
suspend its rules and wave the third
reading of ordinance temporarily
numbered 37 I'm sorry,
>> 36
>> 3625.
>> Second. We have a motion in a second uh
to suspend the rules and wave the third
reading of temporary ordinance 3625.
Any further discussion?
>> Hearing none, please call the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Baylor,
>> Mr. Bischack,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. K,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Luenberg,
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Sully,
>> Miss Teener,
>> yes.
>> And Mr. Wing,
>> Motion to suspend the rules and wave the
third reading of temporary ordinance
3625 passes 10 to zero. Council member
Salt Lake.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. I'd like to
make a motion that council pass and
engross and upon the written record
ordinance numbered 3625.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion to pass, gross, and
enter upon the written record temporary
ordinance 3625. Any further discussion?
Hearing none, please call the role.
>> Mr. Als, yes.
>> Mrs. Berler,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack, yes.
>> Mrs. Kit, yes.
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Luckenberg, yes.
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Sully,
>> yes. Miss Tiner. Yes. And Mr. Wing.
>> Yes.
>> Temporary ordinance 3625 passes 10 to
zero. Temporary ordinance 3725.
>> Sorry. Um, an ordinance to establish new
permanent rideway along a new center
line of connection with the Arbor Valley
Drive rehabilitation project to vacate
the existing Arbor Valley Drive right
away once the new Arbor Valley Drive
rightway is dedicated. and to acquire a
new easement for a water mane in the
connection with the new Lancaster High
School. This is through public works
committee, Miss Tiner and Mr. Adles.
>> Council member Tiner.
>> Second of three readings.
>> Second of three readings on temporary
ordinance 3725,
temporary ordinance 3825.
An ordinance amending part five general
offenses
code of the Lancaster codified ordinance
ordinances and adopting chapter 568
camping prohibited. This is through law
committee. Mrs. Kates and Mrs. Biller.
>> Council member Kes.
>> Yes. Thank you. Second of three
readings.
>> Second of three readings on temporary
ordinance 3825.
Temporary ordinance 3925. an ordinance
to grant the South Central Power
Company, its successors, and assign and
assigns a franchisee for their right to
acquire, construct, maintain, and
operate in the streets their their fair
their affairs alleys,
bridges, and public places of the city
of Lancaster, Ohio, and its successors.
lines for the transmission and
distributions for electric energy to the
city of Lancaster and the inhibitance
inhibitance
thereof for light, heat, power and other
purposes and for the transmission of the
same within through or across said city
of Lancaster and to declare an
emergency. This is through law committee
Mr. Bisjack and Mr. Scoover.
>> Council member Bisjack.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. And I would
like to make a motion that council place
on the ta table temporary ordinance
39-25.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion and a second to table
ordinance 3925. Once again, this is a
non-debatable motion. Please call the
role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Ber,
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Kates,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Lterberg,
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> no.
>> Mr. Sullie,
>> abstain.
>> Miss Tiner,
>> yes.
>> And Mr. Wing,
Motion to table passes 8 to two.
[Music]
>> Now move on to first reading of
ordinances beginning with temporary
ordinance 4025.
>> Council President, u on that last vote,
wouldn't that be 7 to1 with an
abstension?
>> No. No, I'm sorry. 8 to1.
>> You said 8 to1 with an obstension. 8 to
one with an extension. We'll go that
way.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay.
>> Sorry.
>> First reading.
>> Yes.
>> Sorry. Okay. An ordinance to accept the
final plat for the Taylor commercial
subdivision and to declare an emergency.
This is through code enforcement and
zoning committee. Mr. Sully and Mr.
Lockenberg.
>> Council member Si.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. I'd like to
make a motion that council suspend its
rules and wave the second and third
reading of ordinance numbered
temporarily numbered 4025.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion and second to suspend
the rules and the second and third
reading of temporary ordinance 4025. Any
discussion? Council member Sley.
>> None.
>> Thank you. Please call a role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Bller,
>> Mr. Bisch,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Kit,
>> no.
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Luck.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Skunover.
>> Mr. Sullie.
>> Yes.
>> Miss Tiner.
>> And Mr. Wing.
>> Yes.
>> Motion to suspend the rules and move the
second and third reading of temporary
ordinance 4025 passes 9 to1. Council
member Sie.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. I'd like to
make a motion that council pass and
engross and enter upon the written
record. Ordinance temporarily numbered
4025.
>> Second.
>> Have a motion second. Pass gross and
enter upon the written record. Temporary
ordinance 4025. Any discussion, Council
Member Sie?
>> None at this time.
>> Thank you. Any further discussion?
Hearing none, please call the role.
>> Mr. Als, yes.
>> Mrs. Bitler,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Mr. Bischack,
>> Mrs. Kes,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> Mr. Lochenberg,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> Mr. Sully,
>> yes.
>> Miss Tiner,
>> And Mr. Wing,
>> yes.
>> Motion to pass and president upon the
written record. Temporary ordinance 4025
passes 10 to zero. Temporary Ordinance
4125,
>> an ordinance to amend Title 3, chapters
915 and 916 by repeal, repealing and
replacing existing sections 915.04A,
915.05A,
and 916.08
C of the codified ordinances of the city
of Lancaster, Ohio, and to declare an
emergency. This is through water water
pollution committee, Mr. Wing and Mr.
ES.
>> Council member Wang.
>> Yes. This is the first of three
readings.
>> First of three readings on temporary
ordinance 4125.
Temporary ordinance 4225.
>> An ordinance to repeal part 11 planning
and zoning tit zoning code title 3
zoning and property restrictions.
Chapter 1143 parking loading spaces
access and vehicular and pedestrian
connectivity. sections 1143.13
parking and commercial vehicles in
residential residential districts and
the codified ordinances of the city of
Lancaster and to declare an emergency.
This is through law committee, Mrs.
Kates and Mrs. Bitler.
>> Council member Craig.
>> Yes. Thank you, Mr. President. I would
like to make a motion that council
suspend its rules and wave the second
and third readings of ordinance
temporarily numbered 42-25.
>> Second. We have a motion and second to
suspend the rules and we have the second
and third reading of temporary ordinance
4225.
Any discussion?
>> Uh yes, just briefly. Uh the reason we
need suspension is because the current
zoning code conflicts with the parking
code and we are unable to enforce that
um without having this cleaned up first.
>> Thank you. Any further discussion?
>> Hearing none, please call the role.
>> Mr. Als, yes.
>> Mrs. Bller, yes.
>> Mr. Bisch, yes.
>> Mrs. Kra, yes.
>> Mrs. H.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Lockenberg.
>> Mr. Skoover.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Sully.
>> Miss Tiner.
>> Yes.
>> And Mr. W.
>> Motion to suspend the rules and wave the
second and third reading of temporary
ordinance 4225 passes 10 to zero.
Council member Kits.
>> Yes. Thank you, Mr. President. I would
like to make a motion that council pass
and gross and enter upon the written
record. Ordinance temporarily numbered
42-25.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion in a second to pass and
gross and enter upon the written record.
Temporary ordinance 4225. Any further
discussion?
>> Nothing further. Thank you.
>> Thank you. Please call the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Bitler,
>> Mr. Bisch,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Kitz,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Luckenberg,
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Sully,
>> Mr. Deer,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Wing,
>> Motion to pass and gross and enter upon
the written record. Temporary ordinance
4225 passes 10 to zero. Temporary
ordinance 4325.
An ordinance to amend Lancaster codified
ordinance part three traffic code title
7 parking chapter 351 parking generally
by repealing and replacing section
351.16
trucks on residential streets and to
declare an emergency. This is through
law committee Mrs. Kates and Mr.
Bisjack.
>> Council member Kates.
>> Yes. Thank you, Mr. President. I'd like
to make a motion that council suspend
its rules and wave the second and third
readings of ordinance temporarily
numbered 43-25.
>> Second. We have a motion, a second to
suspend rules and wave the second and
third reading of temporary ordinance
4325.
Any discussion? Council member Kits.
>> Yes, we are asking for suspension
because this is the second part of that
code cleanup with the parking code. It
is updated um and there was a correction
to the 14,000 uh that the law director
um provided to the clerk prior to the
meeting.
>> Thank you. Any further discussion?
Hearing none, please call the role.
>> Mr. Als, yes. Mrs. Berler, yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack, yes.
>> Mrs. Kes, yes.
>> Mrs. Hoop, yes.
>> Mr. Lockenberg,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Skunberg,
>> Mr. Sully,
>> yes.
>> Miss Ter, yes.
>> And Mr. Wing,
>> yes.
>> Motion to suspend the rules and wave the
second third reading of 4325.
Passes 10 to zero. Uh, council member
Kits.
>> Yes. Thank you, Mr. President. I'd like
to make a motion that council pass and
gross and enter upon the written record.
Ordinance temporarily numbered 43-25.
>> Second. We have a motion and second to
pass gross and enter upon the written
record. Temporary ordinance 4325. Any
discussion?
Hearing none, please call the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Ber,
>> Mr. Bisch,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Kit,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Luenberg,
>> Mr. Screenover,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Sullie,
>> Miss Teener,
>> yes.
>> And Mr. Wing,
Motion to pass and grant upon the
written record. Temporary ordinance 4325
passes 10 to zero. Temporary ordinance
4425.
>> An ordinance to amend Lancaster codified
ordinance part 7 business regulation
code chapter 709 cultivation processing
or dispensing of med medical marijuana
or adult use of cannabis by repealing
and replacing section 709.05
05 review and reapp reapproval of adult
use cannabis moratorum. This is through
law committee. Mrs. Kitz and Mrs.
Biller.
>> Council member Craig.
>> Yes. Thank you. First of three readings.
>> First of three readings on temporary
ordinance 4425. I did have a question.
Law director. I know this is an
extension of would be an extension of
the existing moratorum for an additional
two years. If the state legislature
would act within that time, can council
revisit it within that 2-year period?
>> You can re repeal and replace.
>> Okay. Thank you very much.
>> Now move on to temporary ordinance 4525.
>> An ordinance to repeal and replace
existing permanent ordinance 21-24
section of setting public improvement
inspection fees pursuant to Langster
codified ordinance or codified 1107.02A
02A and declare an emergency. Um, this
is through law committee. Mrs. Crates
and Mr. Bisjack.
>> Council member Crates.
>> Yes. First of three readings.
>> First of three readings on temporary
ordinance 45-25.
Tabled legislation. We have some, but I
don't believe we're going to be
revisiting that this evening. Um,
unfinished business. Do we have any
unfinished business this evening? Seeing
none.
>> Oh, excuse me.
>> Oh, sorry. I did not see your I did not
see your hand.
So, Council Member Tiner,
>> I just have a question for uh Mayor and
Carrie. So, and I've I've talked to
citizens that aren't even in my ward,
too. Uh they used to be um now they're
in five, but the concern is with the
firehouse, you know, potentially going
on Edy Road. Um who's going to be
maintaining the people out like Cedar
Hill Road um Hunter Trace, Boing, Hoff
Spring,
um Twin Creek because Twin Creek is the
at the um the Y and go Hamburg, this
last street to the right. that that has
been kind of concern if we shut down the
west side one and with you know there's
three railroad tracks plus sometimes
they do close um in bad weather going up
that hill on on Edy Road. So just I mean
just wondering who's going to maintain
all those people out through there even
if the weather isn't bad.
>> Most of the area you're speaking about
is in engine house one's territory not
engine house two. Okay. Because I know
we've you know we've seen two go to but
that it's just a concern. No, it's it's
it is an important question. The the
situation we have here is do we have a
four firehouse model or a three
firehouse model
and that has been debated for a long
long time and uh the current
recommendation is a three firehouse
model but it's by no means a final
conclusion. It's where we're at right
now. I will tell you that we need to add
about 25% more people if we're going to
have a four firehouse model.
>> Well, but I will say that u Lancaster
has three men medics and even Columbus
has two. So that's
>> your point is well taken.
>> Yes. So just certainly a consideration.
Um,
so to Becky's point about, you know,
who's covering what, I will tell you
that the boundaries of each firehouse
will be realigned with the new placement
and to cover the appropriate area. Uh,
the concerns about Ed Road are also
valid. Uh, as you may know, we discussed
here on council floor, uh, we have, uh,
submitted grants for along with the
county for federal funding of widening
and improving Edy Road. The county has
also submitted along with the city
support uh replacement of both bridges.
Uh all those things are important
regardless of where the firehouse is.
They're important for that area of the
city. Um Edy Road is just not quite
ready to handle the traffic it currently
handles. But uh we talked about we own
the piece of property on Edy Road
currently. It's valued at about a half a
million dollars. It saves the taxpayers
that expenditure to buy another piece of
property similar to it nearby. We know
that the northern quarter of the city is
currently unserved by a appropriate
location for a firehouse and hasn't been
served for a long long time. Response
times to river valley highlands for
instance it are significant and more
than what we would like to have. So the
placement of e road is will solve that
problem doesn't mean we don't need
additional facilities. We ought in this
discussion is also moving engine house
one to a more centralized location which
will cover exactly the area you're
speaking of and engine house 3 is is
currently scheduled or planned I should
say to stay on site and be rebuilt at
the same location.
We're growing.
Things are going to change. More people
are moving to Lancaster. These things
now need to be continually evaluated and
see where we're at. Today we say this is
the best plan we have. I think it's a
good plan. I like the locations. I would
tell you they aren't just haphazardly
placed. There's a lot of thought. Uh
we've spoken with outside advisors about
where we might put our plants and how uh
I'm sorry, our fire stations and how
they might serve the city. So this is
where we're at today. Uh but we're
constantly evaluating response times and
locations and what we need for the
future. I envision at some point we will
need a fourth firehouse, but it's not
today. We're currently not able to fund
it today.
So, I hope that answered your question.
>> Well, but you know, like the you know,
like
even though the west side's still there,
you know, if everybody's which everybody
has gone to two men medics, that could
kind of solve a problem too instead of
doing three. I'm I'm just put throwing
that out there for thought. You know,
>> staffing of the medics is a conversation
we're currently having.
>> Okay,
>> because that might solve some of the
four men or four firehouse problems.
>> Our fire professionals are going to tell
you that they they're providing you with
three uh certified paramedics getting
the best service available. I will tell
you, you are right about other cities
and what they do and they do not staff
with three paramedics. they uh might
staff with two and they might have an
EMT driving and they might have a driver
driving and not so it's it's done
different in different cities.
Currently,
we're able to provide three medics in
our squad response and um we're doing
that successfully under our current
staffing levels.
But your point is well taken.
>> Council or service safety director
Woody.
>> Thank you. I will just add that I know I
want to say it was maybe two years ago
the fire department did uh show one of
their studies that by locating the
firehouse to Edy Road and again this was
a long time ago um it showed all of the
response times. I'm sure that that Chief
Scholes would be happy to reshare that
with everyone showing what all the
response times will be, where they're
going to be going and what those
response times look look like by moving
that engine house too over to Edy Road.
>> Well, maybe they need to put that out
for the public. Maybe on the website
that would help, you know, answer
people's questions.
>> Yeah, absolutely.
>> Because I want to make sure every I
mean, I know they do service everyone,
but I just want to people are worried
about that, you know.
>> Yeah, absolutely. But to the mayor's
point, it was very well thought out and
and researched heavily. So I know they
already have that information readily
available and yes, we'd be happy to get
that information if you could put on the
website.
>> Yep.
>> Thank you.
>> Okay. No additional unfinished Oh,
council member Skinover. Was that a Was
that
>> I don't know if it's unfinished business
or new business.
>> Okay.
>> So, addressing the tableing of the
short-term rentals this evening. Okay.
Do we have a plan for that? Was there
What are we That was the third reading.
We're tableabling it. So, what's the
plan for? Council member Crates.
>> I can say that I had reached out to
Chasselyn Carter and spoke with her
about some potential updates and I
didn't see those updates in the current
version. So, I wanted to loop back with
her and find out why we didn't see an
updated version.
>> Okay,
>> that was me.
Yeah, I've had some questions come up
and I I I just want to make sure we're
tight on this before we we put it back
out.
>> That's f I mean that's fine. I just we
didn't have any discussion before there
was a motion to table it. So I was a
little
>> thrown off on what
>> so it just is fine but if it's going to
linger what are we doing with it? So
we're expecting
>> we're requesting changes to it as it
sits
>> or at least discussions. So my concern,
if we want to go through this,
>> you can go ahead.
>> I have concerns with the FBI background
checks. If we have background checks
that are that the resident or owner has
already completed, we should accept
those if they're valid, right, within
that period of time. We don't have
anything in there about that. There's
also some concern around parking and the
restrictions that are in there as well
as um I apologize, my memory just
escaped me. uh the amount of fees per
unit and whether or not that's one unit
if there are multiple units within one
residence and how we're going to work
that out. Those were my questions to
Chasselin that I still have unanswered
and I want to get those worked out.
>> Okay. Okay. Any any further discussion
on that particular topic?
We will move on to new business.
Um currently we will go through uh we'll
start on this side for committee
updates. We'll begin with code
enforcement and zoning committee. Mr.
Sie,
>> u Nothing's really changed from our last
meeting other than we're we tabled the
short term.
>> Okay.
>> And we're going to I'm going to dive
into it a little more. I have I have a
number of questions I didn't bring up,
but
>> Okay. And your next committee meeting is
when we do you know
>> it is in uh November.
>> Okay. Thank you. Uh safety committee,
Council Member Bisjack. Uh, no updates
at this time. Next committee meeting is
October 10th. Thank you. Administrative
services committee, Council Member
Luckenberg.
>> No updates. U, our next committee
meeting will be October 15th, 8:00.
>> Thank you very much. Service committee,
Council Member Ales.
>> No updates. Service committee meeting,
next meeting is next Friday at 8 a.m.
>> Thank you.
>> 95.
>> Law committee. Council member Kates.
>> No updates. The updates were pretty much
in the packet tonight and the next
meeting is November. Thank you. Public
works committee. Council member Tiner.
>> Yes. Um the only update I have I really
I had a complete update last meeting,
but um are we're going to try to move
our meeting from September 12th to the
19th. Just waiting to hear back.
>> Okay. Thank you. We had finance
committee. Is there anything else you
would like to offer? Uh council member
Skuno.
>> No, I mean there's a ton of money
floating around. We all had questions on
some aspect of one or another piece of
legislation. So, we know that we're
looking for water department
new
water plant
budgeted items, I guess, uh, that Denise
is going to get to us. And, and again, I
mean, plenty of valid questions. So, I I
I'm hoping that we start to see from
your
superintendent like their year-to-day
budget in your meetings moving forward.
>> Thank you for that reminder. Yes, we
should be looking for departments to be
providing in committees their
year-to-ate budgets so that we have a
picture moving into next year's budget
season if they could do so. Um, we will
ask Council Member Bitler, do you have
any updates or anything like that that
you would like to share?
>> Not at this time. Thank you.
>> Thank you. Water walk and water
pollution control committee. Council
member Wang.
>> Yes, we had lots of discussion and lots
of legislation come up for first reading
tonight. That covers most of what we
discussed at our last meeting. So, I
think I will leave it there as far as
updates go. Our next meeting is um it's
the third Monday morning of September
and I have that date up. It's the the
15th, 7:30 a.m. in the 1897 conference
room in city hall.
>> Thank you. Economic development council
member Hoop.
>> Yes, I have a few. Um, first of all, the
next meeting is October 30th, which is a
Thursday at 7:30 a.m. Um, and then the
there's a state of the county on
September 30th from 11 to 1 at the
Sheridan Center. You can RSVP with
Stephanie Bosow if you are interested in
going.
Um and then the housing study is
underway and it should be done in
September. And
community development was going through
an amendment of reallocation of prior um
funds and it has been approved by HUD.
So that's good news.
>> Thank you for your
>> Thank you for your update. We appreciate
it.
>> Announcement of scheduled meetings. I
have September 8th, 2025 at 6:30 p.m.
here in council chamber chambers. Um the
next regular sessions of council, I'm
sorry. And September 22nd, 2025 at 6:30
p.m. in council chambers.
>> So I think right now is the time that I
would broach the subject that I will not
be in attendance on the September 8th
meeting. So, we will be um having our
president prom uh council member
Skoonover will be presiding for the
meeting. So, I just wanted to let you
know that. And I'm doing it in public so
I don't get in trouble right now. I
>> was going to ask you out to dinner
afterwards, but I changed my mind.
>> Special scheduled meetings, we have
none. Regularly scheduled committee
meetings, if you want to run quickly
through the list.
>> Sure. I have um four of them. Service
Committee September 5th 8 a.m. City Hall
1897 conference room finance committee
September 8th 8 6 p.m. here in council
chambers public works committee
September 12th at 7:30 a.m. City Hall
1897 conference room water pollution
control service committee meeting
September 15th to 7:30 a.m. in city hall
1897 conference room.
>> Thank you for reading through those. We
had our updates from committee members,
but the more we hear it, the more we'll
have folks knowing when those are.
Reading of bills.
>> I have three. Um, this time I have MNCO
um $7063
for publication of public hearings. Um,
MNCO $288.70
for publication of the ordinances. And
then I have spotlight awards and
trophies. I have $12 for Kathy Bitler's
name plate.
>> Thank you. Um, Mr. President, I'd like
to make a motion we pay the bills.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion, second to pay the
bills. All those in favor, please
signify by saying I.
>> I. All those opposed, same sign. We have
no need for an executive session. I will
take a motion.
>> I'll make that motion that we adjourn.
>> Second.
>> Have a motion, a second to adjurnn. All
those in favor, please signify by saying
I.
>> I.
>> All those opposed, same sign. We are
adjourned. Please remember to sign any
legislation that you had this evening
before you leave. Thank you.
But they live on a pretty
[Music]